let's make a video so I have a really
really great question here that is extra
but super important in 2024 this video
probably will be dated and replaced over
time but the question is hey I'm a
university Professor I'm teaching
machine learning operations just
wondering how do you see the machine
learning Ops scene uh do you think it's
a flash in the pan or do you think it'll
eventually merge with devops is it going
to be its own way for traditional devops
there's a lot to unpack in that question
but it's important that we do unpack
this so this video is a part of a series
of videos that are in a stage of the
beginner boost which is designed to help
you learn um let me read it exactly so I
can get it right but you go to skill.
and you can read this part of it um the
way the way that I'm trying to remind
myself how I worded it so this stage
starts with learn what is required for
the specific career you have targeted
and I'm not I'm going to try really hard
to not redo those other videos but
making the decision about what you want
to do is a separate decision about how
to get the learning and the skill for
this specific thing we've done other
videos about hack the box and all this
stuff for cyber security this question
is fundamentally about machine learning
operations and indirectly about devops
so those are two buzzwords that if
you're brand new to technology you have
no idea what they mean um and I probably
should do another video about devops
um I haven't done one yet and we should
probably do um but this video will
Define what machine learning operations
is so what is OPS period um I believe I
also did another video about whether you
should certify or not and Drew a
contrast between operations and
applications and I kind of going to
refer to all that stuff indirectly now
okay so go back and watch those videos
if you need to understand that but in in
short applications are people who make
new things and make new software uh
whether be web related or whatever and
and they usually have higher paid
salaries uh they're in the developer
category usually and they um they also
lose their jobs much more quickly when
the economy goes bad and I did a whole
video about how to survive late stage
capitalism by learning a little bit of
both go watch that video operations
people this is critical to understanding
machine learning Ops and Dev Ops
otherwise we can't build on that idea so
um the the other side of this is is
operations and operations is kind of
like you know the engineering department
of you know Star Trek it's like they
keep everything running right they they
that's it that's it they keep everything
running and um I I've talked about this
before but I love repeating this quote
bana Torres and Voyager my favorite of
the Star Trek series says um throughout
history Warriors get all the credit and
engineer while engineers build
civilizations and I love that I kind of
feel like that's the same thing for
developers versus Engineers the
developers a lot of time they're also
Builders don't get me wrong but but they
you know they often get a lot of credit
and the operations people are keeping
the infrastructure running and that is a
great segue into what is devops and and
mlops we'll leave devops for another
video uh so iice it to say that and this
is kind of answering the question I
don't think machine learning Ops and
devops are going to be the same and I am
professionally employed as a machine
learning operations engineer in fact
they recently changed my title because
I've been doing so much coding lately
and I think they needed to justify the
pay they were giving me so they changed
my title officially to uh from
infrastructure Eng high performance
Computing machine learning
infrastructure engineer which is kind of
a mouthful to uh my new title is um I'm
sure I get it right I'm doing the same
job but so the other the other what is
it um I can't remember it now it's it's
what is my title it's um uh was it high
performance backend systems uh developer
that's it yeah so backend systems
developer and that's because I'm doing
all the API to submit machine learning
jobs on mass at scale in a way that can
be monitored uh to our you know
extremely large collection of high high
performance gpus uh associated with
computers and stuff and that is the job
that is the machine learning job machine
if you don't know what machine learning
is go back and watch a video about what
machine learning is machine learning is
what enables AI um frankly machine
learning is just one form of AI there's
actually multiple forms but nobody
really talks about any of the other ones
uh machine learning is one very specific
form of AI that that seems to be the one
that's going to win out um and um so
when you hear machine learning think
chbt think you know her think you know
AI in all its forms and AI is is here to
stay I did an entire video called AI is
coming to take my job and go watch that
if you want to understand how AI how I
believe AI is is impacting the
Technology field um whether you'll even
have a job that watching that video is
is going to be important because uh it
does relate to whether or not you want
to do that job or whether you're going
to be good at it um so but how does that
relate to the machine learning
operations profession um as I understand
the title and and by way that is always
a challenge right uh you don't have to
be a beginner to wonder what it means
devops is one go watch the video on
devops I'll make a separate video of
just about devops devops is one of the
most complicated
misunderstood uh confusing terms ever
invented it's almost as bad as data
science is to machine learning people
and I've actually went to a machine
learning Meetup and used the term this
person wants to be a data science and
the Machine learning people rolled their
eyes at me like visibly they were like
oh here we go somebody who's using this
stupid term data science right and these
were you know highly paid professional
machine learning uh people that were
like developing models and dealing with
machine learning models and all that
stuff they were not mlops people and
that brings us back to what is mlops
mlops in my opinion is is what we do all
the things that we do to enable the
machine learning phds and Specialists to
run their models and to do their thing
and how does it differ and this is super
important okay because the Ops on the
end of the ml Ops is what turns it into
an operations career which I think has
tremendous uh
similarities uh and relevance when it
comes to learning things like Linux and
and how to allocate dis partitions and
how to make sure your system doesn't
fall on its face all the questions that
are traditional system administration
which is a term that's fallen out of
Vogue for a site reliability engineer
right they're all operations they're all
keeping the machines running and keeping
the applications up and keeping them
separate from each other so they don't
stomp on each other um that is
operations operations is keeping the
ship going forward um and and when you
add ml into the front of it really the
only thing you're doing in my opinion as
def as you know the the job for mlops is
literally let's enable the the machine
learning infrastructure so so the
higher-end people that are in mlops
they're making decisions like some of
the people on my team are do we want to
go with run AI what kind of gpus do we
want um and you know they're making
decisions The Architects on The mlops
Architects are making decisions about
what's my infrastructure going to be
should I run my machine learning jobs in
the cloud uh what's the cost of that H
what's the cost of renting um you know
100 you know gpus so that I can build my
own cluster on site these are
considerations for The Architects but
the operations people are the ones who
keep that stuff running comment here
you're right my point is the integration
of machine learning and AI into most
apps raises a question will future job
listings assume that devops Engineers
should be proficient in ml Tech deack
um in that sense I think you're asking
about gitops and maybe that you know
what let's ask AI what mlops is shall we
that'll be fun I think I've missed I
think I've got the wrong definition of
mlops and I'm going to leave that in
this video just for that very purpose
what is ml
Ops and I think I think that and this
this is so interesting because this is
so according according to chat gbd 4.0
mlops is short form machine learning
operations the practice of collaborating
communicating between data sciences and
operations professionals to help manage
production learning systems or deep
learning life cycle it aims to
standardize and streamlines deployment
testing and maintenance of ml models in
a scalable and efficient manner similar
to devops and software mlops involves
automating the process of ml model
development including model training
optimization and deployment and there we
go it turns out that the mlops term has
the same problem as the devops term
which I was hoping to avoid but I will
now talk about okay the problem with
devops is if you use the term devops to
uh with an it architect or a vice
president or an executive they will tell
you that devops is the the skills and
soft skills and tasks and and defining
uh the interactions between their
developers and their engineers and
operations people uh it's the
facilitation of of applications
developers it is the science of that the
practice of it in a very general sense
and I I have run into more than one time
because a lot of the parents some of
them were Executives and they gave high
paid one of them after me qu quarter
million job no kidding uh giving uh
giving conferences and stuff um that
particular I'm speak I'm remembering
that specific person I was talking to
she was employed as uh somebody who was
giving you know very expensive U
educational seminars about what devops
was and that person's definition of
devops was the practice of facilitating
all the things without getting into the
need degree details about whether this
person had never heard of gitlab by the
way
you know I if you know anything about
devops and not knowing gitlab is is kind
of I they're like What's gitlab and I'm
like um okay that's funny to somebody
who actually knows about what devops is
and and its implementation and how you
would you know make it run and how to
deploy did UPS getups practice that I'm
not even kidding that's a true story and
and and they were doing conferences in
France about what devops is um and so
anyway um you know and the point of it
is no tangents I know sorry pip shot
thank you um devops okay ml Ops
according to this according to this
mlops suffers from the same problem as
devops and that problem is depending on
who you ask it's either the practice and
the touchy fely thing is the practice
for collaboration and communication
between data scientists and other
horrible turn of machine learning people
hate and operations professionals which
is the engineers that I was telling you
about right so according to this dep
it's the practice this you know nebulous
you know thing that that people pay
$1,000 a seat to go listen to other
people talk to who don't know what G
gitlab
is if you can't tell I have kind of a
pejorative view of that definition
because it's very Dilbert you know I you
can't refer to Dilbert anymore it got
canceled for lots of good reasons but
still it's the whole pointy hair boss
thing right it's like oh and so when you
when you think of memal Ops in that way
um you know it's it's kind of the thing
now tacking Ops onto the end of a word
um has also been used for other things
and and I sense that our our user here
is referring to mlops in the same way
that other people refer to something
called gitops so get Ops is a more
down-to-earth practice of using uh the
te the very specific technology of git
and GitHub um to implement very you know
concrete you know boots on the ground
kind of things such as triggering a
continuous integration and deployment
which is what you know gitlab is really
good at and get up actions um and
triggering that so that it you know your
stuff goes out and gets deployed uh
because through some Automation and that
is that is referred to as get Ops um I
think mlops in the sense that another
general term which is so both mlops and
devops the other four form of that
definition is what are the specific
technology you talk to me and you tell
me oh yeah I'm a devops engineer I'm a
devops person I what I hear is that you
spend almost all your day riding yaml
and playing with kubernetes and
containers and you're dealing with the
cloud and you're facilitating continuous
integration and deployment that's what
you're doing because that's what devops
is the the the solid skill of
implementation of devops using just
watch Alta 4 there's I'm going to I'm
going to plug the altta 4 stream who
does devops all the time and actually
extremely good or or het Tannis does
devops also um you know and you're going
to see concrete skills in use and play
and practice that get good UPS um that
are designed to be Dev Ops they're
they're like here are the practices here
are the Technologies involved here's the
not just the practice but here's the
actual Technologies this is what we're
doing to make devops happen I know
there's a lot there but but when
somebody says well do you think and you
know they clarified the ml Ops being
well what do you think a developer is
going to need to know how to use chat
GPT and machine learning and that kind
of thing you think they're going to need
to that's how I'm reading the the
clarification is that you know the it's
like how how is AI and how is machine
learning going to impact how a developer
does their job and and how do you see Ai
and machine learning kind of coming into
that that that place um I I sense that
that's how that's that's how they're
using the definition of machine learning
Ops it's like how do I use git uh to
make my operations smoother right that
would be gitops um you know how do I use
kubernetes and and containers and VMS
and micr VMS and all that stuff and and
uh to make my developer practices easier
that's devops right and mlops might be
how do I use chbt how do I use AI how do
I use you know whatever all these
machine learning based Technologies to
make operations you know smoother and
and to make the the the development a
little bit better uh and specifically
the question is in is mlops just another
way to say devops um first of all I I
think um that if you're talking about ml
Ops in the terms of the practice
obviously not right machine learning Ops
is more about data science and mixing
that in with how do we do it but if
you're talking about machine learning
Ops from the sense of what is going to
help us make applications better and
easier and how does this how does this
you know get into how does machine
learning play into that I'd say
that it's still largely in the devops
realm which is primarily operations and
um therefore I mean again this gets
really hard because we're not talking
about specific skills we're still
talking about these NE these nebulous
titles and this is a very long video um
to talk about that um the the the point
of it is if you can't go wrong with
operations right and but how much
machine learning do you need to learn to
be an operations person in 2024
and I think that a lot of people are
tuning into this video for that specific
question and my answer is I think you
should learn how to generate and submit
a machine learning model no matter what
and I have not committed to doing a
segment on that specific thing mostly
because I don't know how um and but I
definitely think that in
2024 um not knowing what a machine
learning model is and not knowing how
they are deployed how they are used and
potentially how you could use the
deployed machine learning models that
exist such as chat GP typ G Gemini and
all the other ones as is a serious
negative I would go so far as to say is
that not being able like a level two
knowledge go watch the video about you
know ranking your knowledge in a skill
stack level level one and level two
knowledge of machine learning what's a
data model how do I make one how do I
support one how do I run one what's a
GPU why do I need a GPU what's GPU
versus a CPU those questions I think are
now
mainstream foundational things that
every single technologist has to
understand if you cannot have an
intelligent conversation with someone
about what is used to generate a data
model or to generate you know U
essentially an AI because you don't
understand how those things are created
I would call that a deficiency in
2024 um so I really think I strongly
that everybody including myself and my
own autodidactic you know plan is I will
write and create a data model I will do
my own crunching I will use the tools of
the day in this case pytorch uh tens
pytorch or the competitive tools um and
I'm going to make a model and I'm going
to submit it and I'm going to use it
right and I think that knowing how to do
that um at least knowing the concepts
behind it even if you don't have to do
it to become to before you start
applying for tech jobs H you need to
understand the the steps involved to do
that even if you've never done it and
that I do understand I do I can tell you
how they go about doing these things um
because I support them every day I mean
that's what I do I I I you know write
wrote the API that integrates the
machine automon submissions and stuff
can I can I ever create my own model no
do I know how they created do I know the
difference between the model that's
being created and the model that's being
consumed when it's applied from your
phone or something yes so the answer
that's a very long answer and yes you
need to learn uh machine learn
operations do I think it's going to
change regular operations uh is it going
to get merg in yes I absolutely do I
don't think it's going to be I think
machine learning operations is going to
be consumed by operations in general in
fact I think we're going to start to see
fewer people even distinguish um uh you
know it used to be that this is happened
with lots of terms over the time by the
way so you know it used to be there was
like um like web development right used
to be people would call you web in fact
I would go so far as to say the Bure of
Labor Statistics the numbers changed one
year pretty dramatically between
software developer and web developer
right and I think the reason is because
electron this is a specific example but
it does relate to what I think is going
to happen with machine learning
operations as a separate idea and
category um for a long time you know you
had web developer and then you have you
know software developer and they were
different right and I I think that I
don't know but I think that the reason
that the numbers changed so dramatically
and the software engineering category
shot through the roof software developer
n engineer um and the web people kind of
went down the the the pace of increase
and everything kind of slowed down for
web developer is because fewer and fewer
people were classifying themselves as
web developers and I it's there's
there's I mean as you watch the beginner
Bo you'll see that web technology
somebody was complaining about it
earlier web technology is in everything
now now that we have electron BS code is
web Tech i i people have a hard time
getting their head around that why does
this have to do with machine learning
Ops because the same thing is happening
to machine learning right machine
learning is becoming so ubiquitous and
such a part of every single thing we
have it's going to be very very soon
that we're not going to need to
disambiguate we're not going to be able
to put machine learning behind
operations it's just operations and if
you don't have ai in your operations
then what are you doing what are you a
dinosaur I mean that's where it's going
it's going because it's going to be so
prevalent it's going to be so ubiquity
it's going to be so everywhere that that
there's not going to be a distinction I
also believe that's going to be true of
the term high performance Computing so
high performance Computing or
HPC um is now kind of used I mean I'm on
an HPC you know operations team and we
are distinguished from like the network
infrastructure or whatever but our
umbrella is so huge you could just call
us it right uh or just information
technology at that point but but you
know at some point in history they
created a highperformance Computing you
know because you know we were dealing
with computers that were I suppose more
powerful than desktops or whatever and
so they they made it they made it go
back and forth and they made the
distinction I think high performance
Computing as distinction is going to go
away uh unless it becomes a distinction
primarily designed for Quantum which uh
Freedom just walked in please don't spam
the chat freedom I know you're going to
love this but you know you can now get a
three Cubit um you know desktop computer
that runs Quantum uh a true quantum
computer for $5,000 to start testing
things academically you can't do
anything with it yet um but you know
that the distinction yes this is a
rabbit hole but this is related to the
whole ml Ops ver devops versus
operations thing right to to be
completely fair I think devops has
already been consumed by operations
right and I really do I in fact I tell
people all the time stop calling
yourselves a devops engineer call
yourself an infrastructure engineer or
just call yourself an an Ops engineer
because you know your integration with
the cloud and you know continuous
integration and all those things that
are traditionally assigned to devops
those are now assumed to just be a part
of operations in fact I am literally in
the middle of of writing a GitHub action
that deploys to our internal
infrastructure that has nothing to do
with the cloud or anything like that
it's just it's basically an extension to
anible but it's triggered by git the
point is it's just operations at the end
of the day so so whether you want I mean
if you're trying to decide what to put
in your curriculum and stuff um and you
were making a decision here I would I
would just include understanding machine
learning
um models and that kind of things from a
from a higher theoretical perspective uh
I would include that in all of your
operations training uh for anybody going
into the tech field and then I would
leave machine learning into its own
highly specialized category for people
who want to actually spend their days in
pie torch and tensor flow and writing
models and and cleaning data and and and
all of that thing so that's a pretty
pretty long qu uh question and answer
session about that but hopefully that
that gets to the point of the the the
core of the issue um machine learning is
going to be everywhere uh it's all
operations and um everybody should learn
at least what the concepts are um
hopefully that covers it